我生来便是英格兰的郡长
(U HTRED) I was born an ealdorman of England.
乌特雷德，贝班堡乌特雷德之子，欢迎来到基督的世界
Uhtred, son of Uhtred of Bebbanburg, welcome to the Christian world.
诺森布里亚贝班堡领地的继承人
Heir to the Northumbrian lands of Bebbanburg.
- 你带琥珀石了吗?         - 带了
- You have your stone, amber? - Yes.
这片土地是我们的祖先打下来的，必要时你得为它而死
Our ancestors took this land and you will die for it if needed.
我第一次上战场时才十二岁
I was 12 years old when I Hrst went to war.
杀光他们！
(LORD UHTRED) Kill them all!
我亲眼看着父亲战死
I saw my father killed.
我叔父夺了我的领地,
My uncle took my lands
还向丹麦人俯首称臣
and pledged his allegiance to the Danes.
我劝你一句，别惹乌巴,
My advice for you is to never cross Ubba
永远别跟他动手
and never, never fight him.
我和撒克逊女孩布丽达被入侵者掳走
Stolen by the invaders, along with the Saxon girl Brida,
我先做了奴隶，后来成了拉格纳伯爵的养子
I became Hrst a slave and then a son to Earl Ragnar.
那就是我的家，我的人生
That was my family. My life.
小拉格纳，我的兄弟，还有布丽达，我的爱人
Young Ragnar, my brothen and Brida, my lover.
命运让我成了一个丹麦人
Fate had made me a Dane.
然后命运带来了背叛
And then fate brought betrayal.
我不会袖手旁观，让属于我的东西被人夺走
I will not stand by and have everything taken from me.
贝班堡是我的!
Bebbanburg's mine!
命运主宰一切
Destiny is all.
备马
Horses.
往树林跑
(UHTRED) Head for the woods.
往右, 那道山脊后面有条沟
Go right. There's a gully over that ridge.
找马蹄印，一定会留下马蹄印
(AELFRIC) Hoof-marks. There must be hoof-marks.
附近一定有马蹄印
There must be hoof-marks somewhere.
再去叫些人来，我要找到他
Fetch more men, I want him found.
就算追到麦西亚也要找到他
We'll go as far as Mercia if need be, but I want him found
我要他死
and I want him dead.
- 他长得像我父亲
(UHTRED) Looked like my father.
- 他知道你还活着，会一直找你的      - 让他找去
- He knows you're alive,he'll Keep looking for you. - Let him.
- 我会杀了他，夺回属于我的一切
I'm going to kill him and take back what's mine.
他有军队，还有丹麦人撑腰
He has an army, choice of the Danes.
- 你只有我一个人     - 不
- All you have is me. - No.
我们还有乌巴
We have Ubba.
我们去找他，把实情告诉他
We go to him with our story
借他的军队，为拉格纳报仇
and with his army, we avenge Ragnar's death
然后夺回贝班堡
and we take back Bebbanburg.
- 就这么简单?      - 对
- It's that simple? - Yes.
就是这样
Yes. Tsk, tsk.
布丽达
(UHTRED) Brida.
Brida.
给我唱首歌
Sing me a song.
不唱，我又不是你的吟游诗人
I won't, and I'm not your skald.
说得对，再说你唱歌能把鸟都吓跑
True, and what's more, you'd frighten the birds.
什么?
What?
空气里有种味道
There's a taste in the air.
死亡的气息
Death.
谁干的？谁洗劫了这个村子？
Who did this? Who sacked the village?
- 我动不了 - 你的背断了
- (MAN) I cannot move. - Your back is broken.
- 谁干的？ - 你心里清楚
- Who did it? - You know who did this.
是丹麦人干的
Danes did this.
为什么？
(UHTRED) why?
为什么丹麦人要袭击一个给他们提供粮食的村子？
Why should the Danes attack a village that feeds them?
报复
Revenge.
不过丹麦人杀人需要借口吗？
But since when have Danes need an excuse to kill?
报复？报复什么？
(BRIDA) Revenge? Revenge for what?
嗯？
Huh?
报复什么？说出来，我就给你个痛快
Revenge for what? And I'll end it.
这附近北边有人造反
An uprising north of here.
一个撒克逊奴隶，在婚宴上杀了自己的主人
A Saxon slave. He killed his master at a wedding party.
那个奴隶叫什么名字？
What was the name of this slave?
- 嗯？ - 你一个丹麦人，英语说得不错嘛
- Huh? - You speak English well for a Dane.
他叫什么名字
His name.
乌特雷德
Uhtred.
给我个痛快
End it.
- 说出来 - 说什么？
- Say it. - (BRIDA) Say what?
- 说你心里想的 - 你脑子里装的是屎
- What you are thinking. - You have a turd
- 谢谢
- where there's supposed to be a mind. - (LAUGHS) Thank you.
我们根本不该去贝班堡
We should never have gone to Bebbanburg.
应该让他们以为你已经死了
We should have let them believe that you were dead.
不，你错了
No, you're wrong.
我要让他们知道我还活着
I want them to know that I'm alive.
我必须让他们知道我还活着，因为他们占着我的东西
I need them to know that I'm alive because they hold what's mine.
- 我感觉好多了 - 是吗?
- I feel better for it. - Yeah?
狗在树旁撒尿也一样爽
So does a dog pissing on a tree.
- 你想让我汪汪叫? - 我们该做的
- You wish me to bark? - What we needed to do
是南下去找首领乌巴，把拉格纳的死告诉他
was to ride south to the Chieftain Ubba and tell the story of Ragnar's death.
- 现在去还来得及 - 可现在还有另一个故事
- We'll do it now. - Now, there's a second story
- 一个奴隶杀死主人的版本 - 乌巴知道拉格纳是我义父
- about a slave who killed his master. - Ubba knows Ragnar was my father.
他什么都不知道，我看他早忘了
He knows nothing. I doubt he'll remember.
他会相信自己先听到的那个故事，然后杀了你
He will believe the story he hears first and he will kill you.
你要是会写字，就可以写信给他
If you could write, you could write to him.
他要是识字的话，呵
If he could read, heh.
你让我们没有别的选择
You've left us no choice.
我们必须去找乌巴，然后希望他相信你
We must find Ubba, and hope he believes you.
谢谢
Thank you.
贝奥卡神父
(MAN) Father Beooca.
神父
Father.
赛格沃尔
Segwall.
我在国王大厅等你
I'll see you in the Kings Hall.
大人?
My lord?
阿尔弗雷德大人，是我，贝奥卡神父
My Lord Alfred, it is I, Father Beocca.
大人，国王召集议事了
My lord, the king has called council.
别看着我 神父
(ALFRED) Do not look at me, Father.
- 我是个罪人，一个十恶不赦的罪人 - 大人，我们都是罪人
- I am a sinner. I'm a grievous sinner. - We are all sinners, my lord.
而且我已成婚，我本不该娶妻的
And I am married. I should never have married.
主降下诱惑来考验我们
He sends temptation to test us.
当我们堕落，祂便差遣丹麦人来惩罚我们
When we fail, he sends the Danes to punish us.
我本不该成婚，我应该投身教会
I should never have married, I should've joined the church.
我应该去修道院的
I should've gone to a monastery.
主本能在你身上得到一位忠诚的仆人
God would've found a great servant in you,
但我觉得祂另有安排
but I feel he has other plans.
若你兄长有所不测，人们便会转而依仗你
If your brother were to die, it'd be to you people would turn.
哦，求主保佑他平安
Oh, pray God he does not die.
我又能做个什么样的国王呢?
What kind of a king would I be?
大人，你将是天主的国王
You will be God's king, my lord.
你已蒙罗马圣父祝福与拣选
You've been blessed and chosen by the Holy Father in Rome.
你将是天主的国王
You would be God's king.
-我见过那个折磨着你的女孩了     - 必须将她驱逐
-I have seen the girl who torments you     - Must be banished.
不，她应该被带来服侍你左右
No, she should be brought into your service.
不，我做不到
No. No, I could not.
你要抵挡住她的诱惑，让祂看见你的坚强
You will resist her. You will let him see your strength.
你要感谢祂赐下诱惑，再赞美祂
You will thank him for tempting you and then praise him
赞美祂让你抵住了诱惑
for resisting the temptation.
尽管如此
Notwithstanding,
我有一个消息，您或许该带到议会去
I have news you may wish to take to council.
- 什么消息?     - 大人，北方爆发了英格兰人的起义
- What news? - English uprising, lord, in the north.
起义被镇压了
It was defeated,
但发起这次起义的贵族是贝班堡的乌特雷德
but the nobleman responsible was Uhtred of Bebbanburg.
我认识他
I know him.
他幼时被丹麦人掳走
He was taken by the Danes as a child,
是个虔诚的孩子
a God-fearing child.
- 看来他心里依然是个英格兰人       - 他还活着?
- Clearly his heart remains English. - He lives?
我相信他还活着
I believe so.
他是个勇士，大人     据说他杀了他的丹麦主人和四十个人
He is a warrior, lord. They say he killed his Danish master and 40 men.
他熟悉丹麦人的方式，会说他们的语言，会是个有用的人
Knows their ways, speaks their language. He'd be useful.
- 您可以在议会上提到他        - 他为什么要杀自己的主人?
- You could mention him in council. - Why would he kill his master?
为了仇恨? 为了钱财? 还是为了快意?
For blood? For money? For pleasure?
- 为了英格兰，大人- 但我们怎么知道?
- For England, lord. - But how do we know?
他很可能只是又一个挥剑四方的异教徒
He may well be just one more pagan with a busy sword.
- 但我认识他，大人      - 不，贝奥卡神父，你曾经认识他
- But I know him, lord. - No, Father Beocca, you knew him once.
你认识的是那个孩子
You knew him as a child.
若蒙天主庇佑，我可以派人到各处打探他的消息
I could send word into the country, God willing.
他不过是个虚影，是异教徒口中的传言
He's a ghost. He's a pagan rumour.
若他真能现身，或许才值得一提
Should he become flesh and blood, then he may merit a mention.
但我的信仰，只留给天主一人
However, my faith, I reserve for God alone.
眼下关于那个女孩你说得也许没错
Now, about this girl, you may be right about her.
让她进入我的直属侍从之列
Bring her into my personal service.
并记得为我祈祷
And pray for me.
一如既往，大人
As always, my lord.
阿尔弗雷德
Alfred.
东盎格利亚的埃德蒙国王来信，请求援兵
King Edmund of East Anglia writes for an army.
他们将不可避免地受到丹麦首领乌巴伯爵发起的进攻
An attack by Danish Chieftain, Earl Ubba, is inevitable.
这是两天前的事
This was two days ago.
长途跋涉去他们选好的地方打，这种仗根本不值得考虑
A long march to fight at a place of their choosing is not worth considering.
- 说的算轻的了       - 我倾向于拒绝
- To say the least. - I'm of a mind to decline.
- 理应如此   - 乌巴，就是那个丹麦人，
- And rightly. - Ubba, he is the Dane
埃德蒙国王以前一直供养着的那个？
whom King Edmund has fed and watered in the past?
- 正是   - 也许他是希望乌巴
- He is. - Perhaps in the hope he would pass
借道东盎格利亚去入侵威塞克斯
through East Anglia on his way to invading Wessex.
在我看来埃德蒙国王不值得支援
It's my opinion that Edmund deserves nothing but silence.
太无情了，小奥达
Too harsh, Young Odda.
埃德蒙一心想用善意感化丹麦人，让他们从异教徒皈依基督
It was Edmund's hope to convert the Danes from pagan to Christian
出发点是仁慈，这份心意理应得到称赞
beginning with charity. For that, he deserves praise, surely.
- 若真是这样的话，确实    - 埃德蒙是个虔诚的人
- True, if that was his hope. - Edmund is a Godly man.
我们没理由把他的行为误解为懦弱
We have no reason to mistake his actions for cowardice.
不管他的用意如何，除非出现奇迹
(ATHELRED) Regardless of intentions, barring a miracle,
东盎格利亚终将落入丹麦人之手
East Anglia will fall to Danes.
我们会为这奇迹降临而祈祷
He shall have our prayers for such a miracle.
- 他会需要的      - 威塞克斯不会
- He will need them. - (ATHELRED) He will not
派出一兵一卒，大家都同意？
have one man of Wessex, we are agreed?
- 是，大人 - 是
- Yes, lord - Aye.
那我们必须承认，我们如今孤立无援
Then we must therefore recognise that we now stand alone.
英格兰最后一个王国
The last kingdom of England.
很快就会有威塞克斯的男人站在战场上，直面那支大军
It will soon be men of Wessex staring across a field at the army.
我们必须做好准备，我们要祈祷，要备战
We must be ready. We must pray, we must prepare.
奥达，我需要你密切监视麦西亚、伦敦和东盎格利亚
Odda, I require Mercia, Lundene and East Anglia be watched carefully.
- 掌握先机，才能制胜 - 遵命，大人
- Forward knowledge is everything. - It is done, my lord.
抄书员，我需要每座城镇的铁匠炉日夜不停地烧
Scribe, I require the forges of every town burning, night and day.
我们需要那些炉火锻出的铁
We need the iron those fires can proffer.
遵命，大人
(SCRIBE) Yes, my lord.
最重要的，我需要人
Most of all, I require men.
强壮的、能打仗的人，他们要做好赴死的准备
Strong, fighting men who are prepared to die
因为到最后,，能拯救我们的
because that, in the end, is what it will take to save us.
就是战士的鲜血
The blood of men.
拉文过去常说，"永远别去和乌巴作战"
Ravn used to say, "Never fight Ubba."
看来东盎格利亚刚犯了这个错
Looks like East Anglia's just made that mistake.
我们应该远离这个地方
(BRIDA) We should stay away for now.
去生我们自己的火吧
Build our own fire.
乌巴喜怒无常，他只听众神的旨意
Ubba is unpredictable. He takes his orders from the gods.
我知道他只听一个巫师的话
I know he only listens to a sorcerer.
而且他有点疯
And he's half mad.
你打算怎么去见他?
How will you approach him?
作为一个男人
As a man.
这件事必须去做
It has to be done.
是的，必须去做
Yes, it has to be done.
但我们得保住你的命
But we need to guard your life.
- 怎么做? - 我不知道
- How? - I don't know.
今晚我们该做爱
We should hump tonight.
我们应该做爱，这是天意
We should. it's written.
天意让我们做爱?
That we should hump?
我们的命运就是今晚做爱
Our destiny is to hump, tonight.
- 光想想就让我兴奋     - 今晚你也只能想想了
- I'm enjoying the thought of it. - That's all you'll enjoy tonight.
- 停, 停, 停 - 什么? 怎么了?
- Stop. Stop. Stop. - What? What is it?
我想到办法了
I think I have it.
我们抓一个人质
We take a hostage,
当挡箭牌，保你一命
a shield, a guarantee for your life.
抓谁?
Who?
还不知道
I don't know.
抓他离不开的人
Someone he can't do without.
斯托里，他的巫师
Storri, his sorcerer.
这女人是谁?
(DANE 1) Who is this woman?
她怎么还没躺下（来伺候人）？
Why is she not on her back?
不关你的事，她是给斯托里的
(UHTRED) Not that it's your concern, but she's for Storri.
乌巴送来的撒克逊婊子
A Saxon whore, from Ubba.
我见过你
I've seen you before.
我曾效命于拉格纳伯爵，现在效命于乌巴
I served Earl Ragnar and now I serve Ubba.
- 闭嘴, 女人
-(DANE 2) Quiet, woman.
小子，你肯定还会再见到我的
You'll see me again, I'm sure, boy.
- 听说斯托里在教堂? - 是修道院,
- I'm told Storri is at the church? - Monastery,
他在那儿看押埃德蒙国王，杀他的神父们
looking after King Edmund and killing his priests.
- 有人吗？   - 快走，否则你死定了
- (UHTRED) Hello? - Leave or it will be the death of you.
- 这座教堂是乌巴命令归我的   - 斯托里大人，我给你带来一份礼物
- This church is mine by order of Ubba. - Master Storri, I have a gift for you.
- 哦？  - 是伯爵乌巴送的
- Really? - She's from Earl Ubba.
一个女人？
A woman?
乌巴为什么送个女人来？我不需要
Why would Ubba send a woman? I have no need.
她是个女巫，乌巴想要她死，但又怕被她诅咒
She's a sorceress. He wishes her dead, but is afraid of a curse.
胸也垂，口气也臭，但你会得到报酬的
Saggy tits, stinking breath, but you will be rewarded.
赏金是她脑袋等重的白银
Her head's weight in silver.
女巫？
(STORRI) A Sorceress?
她长了张母狼的脸，会咬人吗？
She has the face of a she-wolf. Does she bite?
- 会，她会咬人 - 把她留给我
- Yes, she bites. - Leave her with me.
我会照乌巴的意思办，让她死得很慢
I will do as Ubba asks and she will die slowly.
老头，你现在是我的人了
You belong to me now, old man.
要是不听我的话，你就死得很慢
And you will die slowly unless you do as I say.
站起来
On your feet.
我们出去走走，给我闭上嘴
We're going for a walk and you will keep your mouth shut.
这太蠢了
This is so foolish.
乌巴会来找我的
Ubba will come look for me
- 他很快就到    - 我说了让你闭嘴
- and he will be here soon. - I said be quiet.
那我就在这等他
Then I'll wait for him here.
我在这等乌巴
I'll wait for Ubba here.
这就意味着只剩你我二人了
That means it's just you and me.
斯托里在哪？ 他应该在这里的
(UBBA) Where is Storri? He's supposed to be here.
埃德蒙
Edmund.
Edmund
能给我们来点麦酒吗？
Can we have some ale?
可怜的东盎格利亚国王埃德蒙
Miserable King Edmund of East Anglia.
你已经有一整晚考虑我的条件了
You have had the night to consider my offer.
你怎么答复？
How do you answer?
- 你是死是活？ - 但愿他死了
- Are you dead or breathing still? - (GUTHRUM) With luck he's dead.
我们已经留了太多人活着了
We allow far too many of them to live as it is.
- 你做不了这个主    - 他还活着
- You allow nothing. - He lives.
谁生谁死，由天主决定
It's God who decides who lives.
我倒觉得，你的天主已经抛弃你了，大人
I would say your God has left you hanging, sir.
若真如此，那也是他的旨意
(EDMUND) If he has done so, it's because it is his will.
把他放下来， 别让他倒在地上
Take him down, and do not to let him fall.
- 给他一杯麦酒，古思伦伯爵也来一杯    - 我不明白
- And ale, and for the Earl Guthrum. - (GUTHRUM) I don't understand.
我们一直都是这么干的，留一半人活命
We do this all the time. We allow half to live.
我说全杀了，只留年轻女人
I say we kill them all. All but the young women.
那谁来耕田？
(UBBA) And who should work the fields?
老女人和孕妇
(GUTHRUM) The old women, the pregnant women.
把他放在那
(UBBA) Put him there.
- 给这位大人倒杯麦酒    - 乌巴伯爵?
- And give the man some ale. - Earl Ubba?
请允许我直说
If I may speak freely.
我认识你
I know you.
我是乌特雷德·拉格纳松，我来是为了告诉你我父亲真正的死因
I'm Uhtred Ragnarson. I am here with the truth of how my father died.
你是拉格纳的奴隶，是你杀了他
Yes, you are Ragnar's slave and you killed him.
我不知道你听到什么，拉格纳伯爵是被丹麦人杀死的
I don't know what you've heard, but Earl Ragnar was killed by Danes.
就是他以前的船长基尔坦和他那独眼的儿子斯文
His former ship's master Kjartan and his half-blind son Sven,
- 他们趁夜偷袭了熟睡中的众人 - 没见我们正在待客吗?
-they led the attack on a sleeping party. - Can't see we're entertaining?
乌巴大人，我告诉你，拉格纳是被丹麦人杀死的
Lord Ubba, I'm telling you, Ragnar was killed by Danes.
- 你给我闭嘴，等着 - 杀了他
- You be quiet, boy. And you will wait. - Kill him.
别跟他废话
(UBBA) Not another word.
封住门，不许他离开
Bar the doors, he does not leave.
古思伦说得对，我们正在招待一位国王
Guthrum is right. We are entertaining a king,
不要再打扰了
so no more interruptions.
我只是想知道，那是谁?
I just have to know, who is that?
嗯?
Hmm?
- 他的眼睛正盯着我     - 也盯着我
- His eyes are watching me. - And me.
什么谁?
Who's what?
- 谁?     - 那边那个半裸的像
- Who? - The half-naked image there.
那是谁?
Who is it?
那是圣塞巴斯蒂安
That is Saint Sebastian.
他曾是罗马士兵，后来皈依（找到）了天主
A former Roman soldier who found God.
在哪里找到的天主?
(GUTHRUM) Found him where?
他在… 他在心中找到了天主，而不是
He ...He found him in his heart, not
- 你想听他的故事吗?    - 我有时间
- Do you wish me to tell you his story? - I have time.
皇帝得知塞巴斯蒂安皈依了天主
(EDMUND) The emperor, discovering that Sebastian had found God,
命令他放弃信仰，他拒绝了
ordered him to renounce his faith, he refused.
于是皇帝下令用箭将他射穿
So then the emperor ordered that he be filled full of arrows
他却活了下来
and yet he lived.
- 他活下来了? - 是的，他活了
- He lived? - Yes, he did.
- 这是真的吗? - 当然是真的
- Is this true? - Of course, it's true.
天主拯救了圣塞巴斯蒂安，愿天主因这份慈悲而受赞颂
God saved St Sebastian and God should be praised for that mercy.
他又活了多久?
For how long did he live?
唉, 可惜他…
Well, sadly he--
皇帝随后又下令将他活活打死
He then ordered him to be clubbed to death.
- 所以他还是死了? - 他去了天堂，所以他活着
- So he died? - He went to heaven, so he lived.
- 我听说过这个天堂    - 什么是天堂?
- I heard mention of this heaven. - What is this heaven?
天堂就是基督徒的英灵殿，只是没有战斗、宴饮和欢爱
Heaven is Valhalla to Christians without fighting, feasting, humping.
天堂就是天堂
Heaven is heaven.
不是什么异教的东西
It's not heathen.
不过，回到你最初的问题
But to answer your very first question,
我已经考虑过你的提议了
I have considered your offer
我同意，我会按你说的继续统治东盎格利亚
and, yes, I will continue to rule East Anglia as you suggest.
我会忍受你的存在
I will suffer your presence.
我会为你提供战马、粮食、钱币
I will provide you with horses, food, coin,
还有人质
and hostages.
你要求的，我都会照做
I will do all that you demand.
但前提是，乌巴大人
But only if you, Lord Ubba,
你和你所有的手下
and all of your men
都必须归顺天主
submit to God.
这是我的条件
That is my demand.
你们必须接受洗礼
You must be baptised.
站进一桶水里，让他们再往你身上浇水
You must stand in a barrel of water and they pour more water over you.
- 他们要给我洗澡?    - 不是
- They want to wash me? - No.
- 是你的体味熏到他们了，乌巴     - 不，是要洗净你的罪孽
- Your scent upsets them, Ubba. - No, to cleanse you of your sins.
只有一位真神，我要求你臣服于他
There is only one God, and I demand that you serve him.
- 现在就宰了他! - 我为什么要臣服于他?
- Kill him now! - Why must I serve him?
因为天主伟大，全能，无上荣光
Because God is great, all-powerful, magnificent.
让他别废话了, 拿出证明来!
Have him stop his yapping and prove it!
好, 说定了, 向我证明你的天主有多伟大, 证明给我看
Ah. Agreed. Prove to me your God is great. Prove it.
证明, 证明, 证明——你看, 就在这里!
Prove, prove, prove-- Look, here!
天主庇佑了圣塞巴斯蒂安
God spared Saint Sebastian.
- 但那人还是死了 - 那是天主的旨意
- But the man died. - It was God's will.
天主能护你不被我的箭射死吗?
Would God protect you from my arrows?
- 如果他真是全能的, 应该能? - 是的, 若是天主的旨意, 他会的
- If he was all-powerful, he would? - Yes, if it was God's will, he would.
那就来试试看
(UBBA) So let us try.
我们朝你射箭, 你要是活下来
We shall shoot arrows at you, and if you survive,
我们全都去受洗
we will all be washed.
- 包括古思伦 - 为什么不呢?
- Including Guthrum here. - Why not?
好吧
Very well.
我仍会继续做国王,
I will continue to be king
但我们就不必去受那个洗礼了
but we will dispense with the need for baptisms.
洗礼之事
The washing.
我撤回请求
I withdraw my request.
但你说你的天主是全能的
But you claim your God is all-powerful.
我要亲眼见到
I want it proven.
剥掉他的衣服，弓箭手准备
Strip him. Archers.
等等
(GUTHRUM) wait.
老实告诉我
Tell me truthfully,
你怕吗?
are you afraid?
天主是伟大的
God is great.
我们走着瞧
We will see.
射
Shoot.
- 射      - 慢着
- Shoot. - Uh-uh-uh.
他们是我的人，只有我才能命令他们射箭
They are my men and only I tell them when to shoot.
射
Shoot.
你是要挨棍子，还是这几箭已经够了?
Do you wish to be clubbed or are the arrows sufficient?
你跑这么远来告诉我杀拉格纳的是丹麦人，不是你
You come a long way, boy, to tell me that it was Danes and not you
that killed Ragnar.
是基尔坦和斯文，大人
It was Kjartan and Sven, lord,
还有其他人
and others.
这是实话，不然我来这儿干什么?
It's the truth. Why else would I be here?
来刺探，来撒谎
To spy, to lie.
- 不是，大人
- No, lord.
- 也许是来杀我? - 不是，大人
- Perhaps to kill me? - No, lord.
- 你受洗了吗? - 奥丁才是我的神
- Have you been washed? - Odin is my God.
但你受洗了?
(GUTHRUM) But you have been washed?
- 是的，大人 - 感觉怎么样？
- Yes, lord. - How did it feel?
- 洗礼？ - 很冷，大人，水很冷
- The washing? - Cold, lord. The water was cold.
没其他感觉？
(GUTHRUM) Nothing else?
我曾是个孩子，大人，如今我是丹麦人了
I was a child, lord. Now I'm a Dane.
对，丹麦人
Yeah, a Dane.
好，现在我们来看看
So, now let us see
奥丁能不能护你躲过箭雨
if Odin will protect you from the arrows.
- 我喜欢这个游戏，扒了他的衣服 - 别靠近我
- I like this game. Strip him. - (UHTRED) Keep away from me.
- 别再靠近了 - 弓箭手
- Not another step. - (UBBA) Archers.
- 我有人质 - 什么？
- I have a hostage. - (UBBA) What?
- 我抓住了斯托里 - 住手
- I have Storri. - Stop.
如果我死，他也死，如果我死，你的巫师也死
If I die, he dies. If I die, your sorcerer dies,
- 你就会失去他的指引了 - 他在撒谎，我闻得出来
- and you're without his guidance. - He lies, I smell it.
我有证据，这是他的符文
I have proof. His runes.
- 我会把斯托里还给你 - 把他脑袋砍下来
- Storri will be returned to you. - Take his head from his shoulders.
- 古思伦，闭嘴 - 让他们打开门
- Guthrum, be quiet. - Have them open the doors.
我离开这里之后，就会放了斯托里
I will release Storri when I am clear of this place.
- 你哪儿都别想去 - 那他就死，你的巫师就死
- (UBBA) You go nowhere. - Then he dies. Your sorcerer dies.
让他们把门打开
Have them open the doors.
总有一天我会杀了你
One day I will kill you.
斯托里会告诉你不是这样的
Storri will tell you otherwise.
关于拉格纳的事，我说的是实话
And I am telling you the truth about Ragnar.
这就是留太多人活命的下场
This is what happens when we allow too many to live.
好极了，柴火
Excellent. Firewood.
你还活着
You're alive.
很好
That's good.
他相信你吗？
Did he hear you?
没有，一个字都不信
He did not. Not a word.
- 他说什么了? - 说要杀我
- What did he say? - That he'll kill me.
就这些?
Nothing else?
斯托里在哪?
Where's Storri?
他说什么了?
(BRIDA) what did he say?
- 他没穿衣服 - 这是必要的
- He's naked. - It was necessary.
他屁股上插了根树枝
He has a branch up his arse.
所以他才没穿衣服
Which is why he's naked.
乌特雷德
(BRIDA) Uhtred.
乌特雷德，他肯定说了什么
Uhtred, he must have said something.
他信了那个谎，他以为是我杀了拉格纳
He believes the lie. He believes that I killed Ragnar.
没有其他办法了
There's nothing more to do.
我们得赶紧离这儿远一点
We should put distance between us and this place.
去哪?
And go where?
哪儿都行，只要不是这里
Anywhere that's not here.
- 我说去找小拉格纳 - 他在爱尔兰
- I say we go to young Ragnar. - He's in Ireland.
- 那就去爱尔兰 - 怎么去? 坐什么? 坐什么船?
- Then we go to Ireland. - How? In what? We sail in what?
- 跟谁去? 丹麦人? - 那就等他回来
- And with whom? Danes? - Then we wait for him.
要是他回不来了，那该怎么办?
What if he doesn't return, what then?
认了吧，我们输了
Accept it, we lost.
- 我们还活着，肯定有原因 - 布丽达，我们已经不是丹麦人了
- We're alive and breathing for a reason. - Brida, we are no longer Danes.
你的兵器怎么收钱?
How much for your work?
一柄长剑
For a long sword?
说说你要什么，我再报价
Tell me what you need and I'll tell you a price.
一把能用一辈子的战士之剑
A warrior sword to last a lifetime.
你是哪边的?
What are you?
撒克逊人还是丹麦人?
Saxon or Dane?
诺森布里亚人
Northumbria.
打好这把剑得花些时日
It'll take some time to make her right,
所以价钱不会低
which means she'll be expensive.
如果做的好，我会用银子付
She's right, I'll pay in silver.
多少?
How much?
十枚，先付一半
Ten pieces. Half now.
六枚，不能再多了
(LAUGHS) Six. No more.
八枚，我给你打把最好的
Eight, and I'll make her my finest.
八枚，如果不是你最好的手艺，你就第一个尝尝她的厉害
Eight, if she is not your finest, you'll be her first.
我想把这块石头嵌进剑柄里
I want this stone set into the handle.
没问题
That can be done.
别卖掉，也别弄丢了
Don't sell it nor lose it.
要来点麦酒吗，大人?
(SERVANT) Ale, my lord?
- 站远一点，姑娘    - 好，就一点点
- You stand too close, girl. - (ALFRED) Yes, just a little.
- 去去粥的味道     - 站远一点
- To take away the taste of the gruel. - You stand too close.
这是浓汤，不是粥
It is broth, not gruel.
- 是吗?
- Is it?
我觉得是，你该感谢天主的恩典
Well, I think it is. You should be thanking God of its goodness
让那些难受的腹痛都消散了
and the banishment of those awful cramps.
我很乐意和你吃一样的食物
I am happy to eat as you eat.
你真是心善, 亲爱的   贝奥卡神父, 来跟我们一起用早餐吧
You are saintly, my dear. Father Beocca, join us for breakfast.
- 我允许你来  - 可惜, 大人, 我已经吃过了
- I dare you. - Alas, my lord, I've already eaten.
你运气真好
(ALFRED) You're fortunate.
大人, 有坏消息 你的侄子埃塞尔沃尔德
Bad news, lord. Your nephew, Aethelwold.
- 坏消息总是和他有关   - 他喝醉了
- (AELSWITH) Isn't it always? - He's drunk.
他睡在宫殿的花园里
He's sleeping in the palace garden.
要把他带去见国王吗? 这已经是本周第二次了
Should I take him to the king? It's the second time this week.
愿天主让他痛苦地死去
May God strike him down, painfully.
- 什么? 什么? - 起来, 小子
- What? What? - (LEOFRIC) On your feet, boy.
等等, 等等, 等等
Wait, wait, wait.
快来, 国王要见你
(BEOCCA) Come on, the king wants to see you.
喝醉了!
Drunk!
什么, 又来了?
What, again?
你觉得这像话吗?
Do you think this is fit?
都出去, 留我们单独说话
Out, all of you, leave us.
- 你觉得这像话吗? - 我受了虐待
- Do you think this is fit? - I have been mistreated.
你亲眼看到了 我要求——
You saw this for yourself. I demand that this--
- 这头混蛋受到惩罚 - 埃塞尔沃尔德,
- This bear is punished. - (KING AETHELRED) Aethelwold,
你年纪不小了, 还是叫人失望
your years do not hide the fact you are a disappointment.
- 为什么? - 如果你还要问这个, 你父亲
- Why? - That need to ask tells your father
- 就什么都明白了 - 明白了什么?
- all he needs to know. - What?
明白了你不适合继承王位
That you are an unsuitable heir. That is what.
- 那我会改变的 - 你该改
- Then I will change. - You should.
- 我会的 - 听着, 我只要求一件事
- I will. - Look, all I ask
你得快点成长为一个真正的男人
is that you become a man, and quickly.
就从今天开始
Today.
从今天开始, 我保证
Today, I promise.
我可以告退了吗?
Am I excused?
大人
My lord.
我怀疑他根本不是我的儿子
I'm not convinced he is my son.
他母亲要不是已经死了, 我早就以通奸罪砍了她的头
If his mother was not already dead, I'd have her beheaded for adultery.
如果我在即将到来的战斗中阵亡,
If I'm to fall in the battles that will come,
他不能继承王位
he cannot be king.
- 你倾向的是阿尔弗雷德吗 - 是的
- You favour Alfred? - I do.
即便他身体常常羸弱?
Even though he is often weak in body?
病痛没有把他困在床上, 这正是我弟弟的坚韧所在
His illness does not tie him to bed, shows the strength of my brother.
阿尔弗雷德是我的继承人, 他自己也清楚
Alfred is my heir. He knows it.
时机一到, 奥达, 我的朋友,
And when the time comes, Odda my friend,
你必须引导贤人会议做出这个选择
you must steer the witan to make this choice.
大人
My lord.
搞完了
(UHTRED) it's done.
眼下应该安全了
Should be safe for now.
据说丹麦人很少来这里
They say Danes rarely come here.
斯托里跟你说了什么, 让你把他的嘴给堵上, 还有......
What did Storri say to you to make you bind his mouth and, uh...
他下了一个诅咒
He threw a curse.
说什么?
Saying what?
不重要
It's not important.
我用树枝回应了
I responded with the branch.
你在干什么?
What are you doing?
你知道我在干什么
You know what I'm doing.
我要用一个吻解除最后一道诅咒
I'm removing the last curse with a kiss.
我不想
I don't want to.
你若想去投奔丹麦人, 那就去找个新主人
If you want to go to the Danes, then go find a new lord.
他们想杀的是我
It's me they wish to kill.
- 你说话像个孩子 - 我是在给你选择
- You sound like a child. - I'm offering a choice.
- 你是在用屁股说话  - 我正坐在我的屁股上
- Talking through your arse. - I'm sitting on my arse.
那你屁股比你聪明, 它能一心二用
Your arse is cleverer than you, it can do two things at once.
谢谢
Thank you.
你这女人, 嘴够毒的
Your tongue is sharp, woman.
- 再给我看一遍 - 不
- Show me again. - No.
你说得对
You're right.
我们不能去找小拉格纳
We can't go to young Ragnar.
但我们应该等他来找我们
But we should wait for him to find us.
他会来的, 他想知道真相
Which he will. He will want to know the truth.
在那之前, 我们得活下去
In the time between, we stay alive.
打发时间
We pass the time.
怎么打发?
Doing what?
我给她添了几分姿色
I've given her some beauty.
但她不过是个工具, 仅此而已
But she is a tool, no more, no less.
她正是我期望的样子
She is exactly as I'd hoped.
- 我们说好十个? - 我们说的是八个
- We said ten? - We said eight.
她值十个
She's worth ten.
- 谢了 - 谢了
- Thank you. - Thank you.
大人, 有人在打听你的下落
Lord, men have been asking of you.
还有你的女人
And your woman.
- 丹麦人还是撒克逊人? - 随你选
- Danes or Saxon? - Take your pick.
五个或者更多
Five or more.
让她颤鸣吧
Make her sing.
我们得走了, 有人在找我们
We should leave. There are men looking for us.
是乌巴的人? - 不知道
(BRIDA) From Ubba? - I don't know.
撒克逊人和丹麦人都在找我们
Saxons and Danes are looking for us.
我们这一路好像到处都在树敌
We seem to be collecting enemies as we go.
去找马, 快走快走!
Get to the horses. Go, go, go!
让开  让开
(UHTRED) Out of the way, out the way!
布丽达, 马就在那边
Bride. The horses are just there.
等等, 还有一个, 我们得走了, 跟我来
Wait, there is another. We have to go. Come.
快走, 快走, 让开!
Move, move, move, out of the way!
- 布丽达, 去开门 - 等等
- Brida, the door. - Wait.
等着, 等着
Wait. Wait.
现在!
Now.
你说得对, 我们该走了
You're right. We should leave.
不管是谁派他们来的,
Whoever sent them,
乌巴还是你叔父, 都不会罢手, 还会有更多人来
Ubba or your uncle, they won't rest. There'll be others.
我没有援兵就回不了家
I can't go home without help.
乌特雷德, 你应该放弃贝班堡
Uhtred, you should forget Bebbanburg.
不
No.
不, 我不会就此消失
No, I won't vanish.
什么都不会变, 基尔坦和我叔父要为拉格纳的死付出代价,
Nothing changes. Kjartan and my uncle will pay for Ragnar's death
- 那片土地也必须回到我手中 - 但怎么做?
- and I will have those lands. - But how?
靠谁的帮助?
With whose help?
- 你自己也说了, 我们只有乌巴—— - 英格兰人
- You said yourself, we only have Ubba-- - The English.
如果我们在丹麦人眼里已经是死人, 那就别无选择
If we're dead to the Danes, we have no choice.
英格兰根本不存在
There is no England.
- 丹麦人占了英格兰 - 不, 南边还有一个地方
- The Danes have England. - No, there is one place, south of here.
- 那就是威塞克斯 - 他们看见你就会杀了你
- it's Wessex. - They'll take one look and kill you.
而乌巴会把我当英格兰人杀掉
Whereas Ubba will kill me as an Englishman.
跟着埃塞尔雷德国王, 我们就有一线生机
With King Aethelred we have a chance, of everything.
你怎么说?
What do you say?
跟我来?
Come with me?
他们为什么盯着我们看?
Why do they stare?
- 他们觉得你好看 - 哼
- They think you're pretty. - Huh.
或者他们从没这么近见过丹麦人
Or they have never seen a Dane so close.
但他们会见到的
But they will.
- 我们有事要见埃塞尔雷德国王 - 滚回家去!
- We have business with King Aethelred. - (MAN 1) Go home!
当心
(MAN 2) Careful.
我说了, 我们有事要见国王
(UHTRED) I say we have business with the king.
你听不懂英语吗?
Do you not understand English?
你说的那叫英语, 浑球? 你说话跟丹麦人一个腔调
Is that what you're speaking, arseling? You sound like a Dane.
你一个种地的, 打扮得像个战士干什么?
Why do you dress as a warrior when you're a farmer?
我种地?
Farmer, am I?
嗯，我敢说，我这农夫随时都能赢过你。
I'd wager this farmer against you at any time.
我们是来和平觐见国王的
We are here to see the king peaceably.
- 乌特雷德, 你在干什么? - 怎么了?
- Uhtred, what are you doing? - What is it?
- 见血就停还是打到死? - 乌特雷德
- First blood or to the death? - Uhtred.
我要劈开你的脑袋, 小子, 所以一个接一个来
I'll be splitting your skull, boy, so one follows the other.
- 乌特雷德?
- Uhtred?
贝奥卡神父
Father Beocca.
- 我的天     - 神父, 认识这个浑球?
- My goodness. - Know this arseling, Father?
认识, 是的, 认识 乌特雷德, 你——
(BEOCCA) I do. Yes, I do. Uhtred, you're--
你都长这么大了
You're fully grown.
而你却老了
And you're old.
是啊
I am.
你是个男人了
You're a man.
他说有要事求见国王
(LEOFRIC) He claims business with the king.
是的, 是真的
Yes. Yes, it's true.
不是求见国王, 是找阿尔弗雷德
But not with the king, with Alfred.
- 你为他担保? - 我为他担保, 是的
- You vouch for him? - (BEOCCA) I vouch for him, yes.
这定是天主派你来的
God has sent you surely.
你已经是个男人了
You're a man.
神父, 这是布丽达
Father, this is Brida,
我最好的朋友
my greatest friend.
一个女人
A woman.
- 是的 - 没错
- (UHTRED) Yes. - I am.
- 我有胸 - 我看见了
- I have tits. - I see.
让人喂好他们的马, 饮足水
Have their horses fed and watered.
我去通报阿尔弗雷德你们到了
And I will inform Alfred you're here.
- 神父, 要收他们的武器 - 为什么不去通报国王?
- We need their weapons, Father. - Why not inform the king?
国王正忙着
The king is busy.
但你会喜欢阿尔弗雷德的
But you will like Alfred.
他是个了不起的人
He is an impressive man.
跟我来
Come.
你喜欢吗?
Do you like it?
喜欢
I do.
真美
It's beautiful.
- 你可以在这里歇息，多安静啊 - 宁静
- You could rest here. it's so quiet. - (ALFRED) Peaceful.
罗马人修建这座庭院，就是为了这个，求一份宁静
The Romans, they built this courtyard for just that purpose. Tranquillity.
- 你是阿尔弗雷德？ - 正是
- You're Alfred? - I am.
- 大人 - 你就是乌特雷德
- My lord. - (ALFRED) You are Uhtred.
我听说你是个了不起的勇士
I hear word you are a considerable warrior.
还没真正经历过考验，大人，还没有
(LAUGHS) Not been tested, lord. Not yet.
我只是运气好
And I've been lucky.
运气好，那也是好事
Well, luck is good.
我的勇士们也是这么说的
Or so my own warriors say.
只是这运气背后的神学道理，我还没想通
Now, I haven't quite worked out the theology of luck.
若一切皆由天主主宰，运气又从何而来？
Can there be luck if God disposes?
如果你的天主与你同在，你自然是个幸运的人
If your God is with you, you're a lucky man.
是，你说得对
Yes. You're right.
说得简单，但你说对了，跟我来
Simply put, but you are right. With me.
我们进去说几句
We shall talk inside briefly.
我有许多时间是在这里度过的
I spend much of my time in here.
乌特雷德，你识字吗？
Do you read, Uhtred?
小时候贝奥卡神父教过我
(UHTRED) Schooled as a child by Father Beocca.
但我不是个好学生
I was not a good student.
- 文字之外，有很多东西要学 - 这我毫不怀疑
- There's much to know outside letters. - (ALFRED) I'm certain there is.
但不要小看文字的力量
But do not underestimate the power of the written word.
一个人死后，若无文字记载，他很快就会被人遗忘
When a man dies, if nothing is written, he is soon forgotten.
就拿拉格纳伯爵来说，还有谁记得他？
For instance, who is remembering Earl Ragnar?
你知道拉格纳？
You know of Ragnar?
贝奥卡神父跟我提起你很多次了, 乌特雷德
Father Beocca has talked much about you, Uhtred.
他以为你被俘了
He believed you a prisoner.
沦为拉格纳伯爵的奴隶, 是这样吗?
Slave to Earl Ragnar. Is that the case?
拉格纳待我如父
Ragnar was a father to me.
我深爱着他
I loved him.
但在约克, 人们都说是你杀了他
Yet in Eofervvic, they're saying that you killed him.
他们在撒谎
They lie.
基尔坦, 基尔坦, 这个名字是这样念的吗?
Kjartan. Kjartan. Is that how you pronounce it?
- 基尔坦 - 基尔坦
- Kjartan_ - Kjartan,
是从拉格纳的死中得益最大的人
has benefited most from Ragnar's death.
他取而代之, 如今已是基尔坦伯爵了
He has taken his place and is Earl Kjartan now.
- 一方大领主, 手握船队 - 这些都有记录?
- A great lord, with ships. - That's written down?
凡是我探到的关于敌人的消息, 都会记录在案
Whatever I discover about enemies is written down.
基尔坦杀你对他有利, 不是吗?
It's in Kjartan's interest to kill you, is it not?
他不想让拉格纳的儿子听到另一个版本
He would not want Ragnar's son to hear a different tale.
他不想让他听到真相, 没错
He would not wish him to hear the truth, no.
没错, 还有头领乌巴,
(ALFRED) No, and the Chieftain Ubba,
尽管他本人已北上远行
although he himself has now travelled north,
他派人去了麦西亚, 打听你的下落
he has sent men to Mercia asking of your whereabouts.
但不是关心你是否安好, 我猜?
But not your welfare, I surmise?
这些消息你都是从哪儿得来的?
How do you come by all of this?
各个王国里我都有耳目
I have eyes and ears in each of the kingdoms.
有朝一日
One day,
我希望所有的王国能合而为一
it is my hope that all kingdoms will become one,
在同一位天主的庇护下团结一心
united under one God.
一位国王?
One king?
如果所有人都能达成共识, 是的
If all men can agree, yes.
英格兰如今只剩威塞克斯
All that remains of England is Wessex.
一个英格兰的诞生,
The birth of an England,
一个叫做英格兰的统一王国的构想
the idea of a single kingdom
called England
必须从这里开始
has to begin here.
别无他处
There is nowhere else.
但威塞克斯还能撑多久?
But for how long will Wessex remain?
威塞克斯的命运, 要由英格兰人来决定, 所有英格兰人
The fate of Wessex will be determined by Englishmen, all Englishmen.
只有团结起来守住威塞克斯, 才能有英格兰
Only by joining together and saving Wessex can we have England.
只有守住威塞克斯, 才能有诺森布里亚
Only by saving Wessex can we have a Northumbria.
才能有贝班堡
A Bebbanburg.
如果威塞克斯守不住呢?
And if Wessex can't be saved?
那我们就什么都没了
Then we are all no more.
祷告者们
Prayers.
我有点不舒服
And a little discomfort.
我猜测
I will summarise.
丹麦人正在集结一支大军
The Danes are gathering a great army.
- 他们已经集结了一支军队 - 在哪里集结?
- They have gathered an army. - Gather where?
他们从伦敦沿河上行, 到了雷丁厄姆
They moved upriver from Lundene to Readingum.
此刻正在安营扎寨
They are settling as we speak.
你说乌巴在北边, 那谁来领军?
You say Ubba is north, so who leads?
- 古思伦伯爵统领他们 - 我认识古思伦
- The Earl Guthrum leads them. - I know Guthrum.
我们得把每一分优势都用上
We will need every advantage.
贝奥卡神父认为你
And Father Beocca considers you,
贝班堡的乌特雷德, 是个有用之人
Uhtred of Bebbanburg, to be an advantage.
而我认为你来这里不过是为了躲避
Whereas I believe you are here solely to hide,
为了保全自己
to save yourself.
我看着你
I look at you
看到的是个丹麦人
and I see a Dane.
我看到的是无处为家的乌特雷德, 只顾自己, 不管任何人
I see Uhtred of Nowhere, who cares for no one but himself.
我得去祈祷了, 你来吗?
Now, I must go to prayers. You will join me?
- 如果大人不介意的话就不来了 - 我们两个都不去
- If my lord will excuse me. - (BRIDA) Us both.
当然不介意
Of course.
我早料到了
I expected as much.
- 贝奥卡神父 - 大人?
- Father Beocca. - (BEOCCA) Lord?
- 带你的客人去用些茶点 - 遵命, 大人
- Take your guests for refreshments. - I will, my lord.
他们可以留在温切斯特, 但我要你负责
They may remain in Winchester, but I hold you responsible.
是, 大人
Yes, lord.
你该跟着去祈祷的, 那样能拉近你们的关系
You should've gone along and prayed, it would've bonded you.
他以为我们是异教徒
He believes we are pagans.
阿尔弗雷德真正相信的是丹麦人抛弃了你
What Alfred believes is that the Danes abandoned you.
乌巴抛弃了我们, 但还有别的首领
Ubba has abandoned us, there are other lords.
大多数首领, 要不是全部, 都听命于乌巴
Most, if not all, follow Ubba.
- 相信我, 你们已经被抛弃了 - 你觉得你知道关于丹麦人的一切，是吗
- Believe me, you have been abandoned. - You know everything about Danes,don't you?
这边走, 我有样东西想给你看
(BEOCCA) This way. I wanna show you something.
贝班堡的契约
The Charters of Bebbanburg.
- 对, 土地登记簿 - 你把它们保住了
- (BEOCCA) Yeah, the land books. Yeah. - You kept them safe.
我已经让阿尔弗雷德看过了
I have shown them to Alfred.
他知道你才是合法的郡长
He knows you are the ealdorman by right.
我会继续保护他们的安全
I will continue to keep them safe,
但乌特雷德, 你必须像个郡长那样行事
but, Uhtred, you must behave like an ealdorman.
那些契约没有任何意义, 诺森布里亚已经是丹麦人的地盘了
The charters have no meaning. Northumbria belongs to the Danes.
诺森布里亚不属于丹麦人, 是被他们抢走的
(BEOCCA) It does not belong to Danes, it has been stolen.
你想要财富就去抢, 你不能无视这个事实
(BRIDA) You want wealth, you take it. You can't ignore what's true.
如果丹麦人在雷丁厄姆, 我就去
If the Danes are at Readingum, I'll go.
- 什么? - 去做什么?
- What? - For what purpose?
去打探消息
(UHTRED) For knowledge.
我们已经有消息了, 你最好离丹麦人远点
(BEOCCA) We have knowledge and you should stay away from the Danes.
去打探新消息, 你们知道他们在哪里安营
For new knowledge. You know where they're settling,
- 但不知道为什么 - 我们知道他们的人数和位置
- but you don't know why. - We know their number and position.
但不知道他们的意图
Not their intention.
我是囚犯吗?
Am I a prisoner?
他们的意图就是进攻
Their intention is to attack.
什么时候?
When?
春天, 永远都是春天
Spring. It is always spring.
我要去雷丁厄姆, 在哪儿?
I'll go to Readingum. Where is it?
- 太危险了 - 对我来说不危险
- it's too dangerous. - (UHTRED) Not for me.
- 我是个不信教的丹麦人, 记得吗? - 为什么要替阿尔弗雷德做探子?
- I'm a godless Dane, remember? - (BRIDA) Why spy for Alfred?
他是英格兰的郡长
He is an ealdorman of England.
大人
(BEOCCA) Lord.
关于将异教徒改信基督教一事,
Regarding the conversion of the pagans to Christianity,
- 大人? - 我们该如何决定什么才是合宜的做法?
- Yes, lord? - how do we decide what is proper?
是要启发他们, 还是杀了他们?
To enlighten them or to kill them?
传播天主的福音, 当然是我们的使命
Spreading God's word is, of course, our mission.
但我担心那些异教徒, 真正的异教徒,
But I fear that the pagans, the true pagans,
必须先亲眼见识、亲身感受祂的力量
must first witness and feel his power.
- 乌特雷德会回来? - 是的, 他会回来
- Uhtred will return? - Yes, he will return.
是的, 但他会以什么面目回来? 以什么身份? 成了什么人?
Yes, but how will he return? As who? As what?
- 我了解这个孩子-- - 但这个孩子如今已是个男人
- I know this boy-- - But this boy is now a man.
- 我了解他的灵魂 - 贝奥卡神父, 他没有灵魂
- I know his soul. - Father Beocca, he has no soul.
而你自己也说过
And you say yourself,
那些异教徒需要感受天主的力量
the pagans need to feel the power of God.
这就写在这里, 就是现在
It is written, now, here.
你退下吧
You may leave me.
且看这几日会带来什么, 大人
We shall see what the days bring, my lord.
如果他们打算在冬天休整
If resting through the winter was their intention,
就该留在伦敦
they would've remained in Lundene.
你才是阿尔弗雷德的奸细, 下一步就是替他杀人, 你愿意干吗?
It's you who's AIfred's spy. Next step is to kill for him. Will you?
告诉我, 如果我们渡河去找古思伦, 会发生什么?
Answer me this, if we were to cross and find Guthrum, what would happen?
他会把我们都杀了
He'd kill us both.
我们不欠他们任何东西
We owe them nothing.
阿尔弗雷德需要了解丹麦人的情况, 我需要得到他的信任
Alfred needs to know about the Danes, I need his trust.
你以为他会把贝班堡交给你, 要是你想错了呢?
(BRIDA) You'd think he'd deliver you Bebbanburg, what if you're wrong?
阿尔弗雷德, 你召集贤人会议所为何事?
Alfred, you have called council for what reason?
大人, 恕我冒昧, 或许没什么大事, 但有个异教徒
Lord, forgive me, it may be no reason, but we have a pagan
声称掌握有关丹麦军队的情报
who claims knowledge regarding the Dane army.
- 异教徒? - 请恕我冒昧, 大人
- (AETHELRED) Pagan? - Forgive me, lord,
他是贝班堡的乌特雷德，我以人格担保他说的话
he is Uhtred of Bebbanburg. I vouch for his word.
- 乌特雷德 - 大人
- (AETHELRED) Uhtred. - Lord.
我去过雷丁厄姆，亲眼盯着丹麦人看
I've been to Readingum, watched the Danes.
他们不是来定居的，要是打算定居，就不会离开伦敦
Their intention is not to settle. If it were, they would've remained in Lundene.
你的意思是，他们要发起进攻？
You are saying, what, they intend to attack?
- 是的，大人 - 我们知道
- I am, lord. - (ODDA) We know.
- 开春他们就会打到门口来 - 用不到开春，就是这几天
- Come spring, they'll be at our door. - (UHTRED) They will be within days.
- 我确定 - 你怎么能确定？
- I'm sure. - How can you be sure?
- 地面还泥泞着—— - 他们已经在祭祀了
- The ground is sodden-- - They made sacrifices.
普通士兵捉来寒鸦杀掉祭神
Ordinary warriors caught and killed birds, jackdaws.
这是出战前几天才会做的事
This is done in days before battle.
- 他们还饿着肚子 - 也许那些鸟就是他们的口粮
- And they are hungry. - Perhaps they have eaten these.
他们人多马多，粮草却很少
They've many men and horses, few supplies.
第一步肯定是抢一座粮食和牲畜都充足的城镇
They'll first seize a town rich with grain and livestock.
这一带我不太熟，但我走过不少地方
I don't know the country well, but I've travelled.
我觉得阿宾顿就是这样的地方
I believe Abbendum is such a place.
要想打败丹麦人，就得在他们去阿宾顿的路上截住他们
To defeat the Danes, you must meet them on the road to Abbendum.
大人，就是这几天
They'll be within days, lord.
你一个人去了雷丁厄姆？
(ALFRED) You went to Readingum alone?
和布丽达一起去的
With Brida.
- 为什么单独去？ - 有什么不对吗？
- Why alone? - (UHTRED) Why not?
因为你这辈子大半时间都是跟着丹麦人过的
Because for most your life, you lived as a Dane.
你看起来像丹麦人，说话也是丹麦口音
You look like a Dane, you speak the language of a Dane,
我估摸着，你设陷阱的手段也跟丹麦人一模一样
I surmise you can set a trap like a Dane.
大人说得对，他把我们当寒鸦了
Agreed, my lord, he imagines we are jackdaws.
去阿宾顿路上的哪个地方?
(AETHELRED) Where on the road to Abbendum?
- 你会选在哪里迎战? - 就是那个叫阿塞克山岗的地方, 大人
- Where would you choose to meet--? - The place called Asec's Hill, lord.
- 是你选的还是古思伦选的? - 我亲眼看过, 那里山道狭窄
- You or Guthrum would choose? - I've seen it, the pass narrows.
敌人根本没法包抄我们
You cannot be out-flanked.
丹麦人要仰攻上坡, 那可不好打
For Danes to fight uphill, it'll be difficult,
不过他们会很自大, 他们根本不把撒克逊人放在眼里
they'll be confident, they don't fear Saxons.
为什么? 他们为什么不怕我们?
Why? Why do they not fear us?
他们觉得你们不过是一群庄稼汉, 别无长处
They believe you to be farmers, nothing more.
所以就算阳光正好打在他们眼上, 他们也会往上冲
So even with the sun in their eyes, which is possible, they will climb
这对我们反而是个机会
and that can be to our advantage.
对我们是个机会, 他说得倒轻巧 你才在这里待了几天
To our advantage, he says. You've been here for days
你就说你是威塞克斯人?
and you claim to be of Wessex?
简直胡说 这一切来得也太凑巧了, 大人
This is nonsense. This is all far too convenient, my lord.
大人, 我的剑是撒克逊人打的, 我这把剑是为威塞克斯而战
My lord, my sword was made by a Saxon. My sword is for Wessex.
- 贵族说话时不得插嘴 - 奥达
- Don't interrupt a noble when speaking. - (AETHELRED) Odda.
我认为此人和他的话都是冒牌货
I believe this man and this bag of rags to be impostors.
- 没有哪支军队会在入冬之前出征-- - 小奥达, 你够了!
- No army marches as winter approach-- - Young Odda, enough from you!
大人
My lord.
你
You.
你的话给这个会议提供了不少值得商议的内容
You have spoken and given this council much to discuss.
陛下
(UHTRED) My lord.
阿尔弗雷德, 他是你请来的 现在怎么办?
Alfred, he's here at your invitation. What now?
丹麦人若真的进军, 我们就必须迎战
Should the Danes march, we must face them.
我宁可站在山顶, 也不愿在平地上硬拼
And I would rather be at the top of a hill than on the flat.
我说, 我们向阿塞克山岗进军
I say we march to Asec's Hill.
但把他关起来
But take him.
- 把他们两个都关起来，看好了 - 遵命
- Take them both, make them secure. - Lord.
这是什么意思? 我说的都是实话
What is this? I have spoken the truth.
- 我说的都是实话,贝奥卡神父 - 大人,求您了
- I have spoken the truth. Father Beocca. - (BEOCCA) My lord, please.
- 贝奥卡,救我!贝奥卡! - 要有信心!
- Beocca, help me! Beocca! - (BEOCCA) Have faith!
停住!停住!
Hold! Hold!
左翼,原地不动
Left flank, hold.
停住!
Hold!
弓箭手准备!
Archers ready!
听我号令
(AETHELRED) On my command.
为了天主,为了威塞克斯,为了英格兰!
For God, for Wessex, for England!